Guide to the Student Unrest at Yale Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Student unrest at Yale collection
1769-2007
RU 83
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.88
(11 boxes, 1 folio folder)
The materials consist of petitions, correspondence, photographs, notes, and clippings documenting various student riots and protests at Yale.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 41 (YRG 41), Material documenting Yale student life.
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Arrangement
The materials are aranged by accessions
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of petitions, correspondence, photographs, notes, and clippings documenting various student riots and protests at Yale.
Riots; Student movements; Student protesters; Student strikes; Petitions; Photographs; Yale College (1718-1887) -- Students; Yale University -- Students
- Materials documenting Yale student unrest, 1774-2007; Accession 19ND-A-379
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in Box 4, Folders 32-33 are restricted until January 1, 2036 and January 1, 2045 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Conic Section Rebellion, 1825
    - Petitions, statements by the College, student apologies, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bread and Butter Rebellion 1828
    - Petitions, dismissals, statements by the College (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1828 August-September (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Apologies from students of the class of 1829 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Apologies from students of the class of 1830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Apologies from students of the class of 1831 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Apology from one student from the class of 1832 and one unknown (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Album commemorating the "Great Rebellion" with autograph sentiments by Yale students. Owned by George Edward Hand (Y. 1829), 1828 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - Conic Rebellion, 1830
    - Statements and drafts of statements, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Petitions and dismissals (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1830-1831 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Hush Hall"
    - Petition for "full publicity as to the purpose and character of the new addition [building] to the campus", [1927?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Snowball Riot 1959 Mar
    - Reports and statements of witnesses (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Report of the "ice cream" riot of 1952 and statements of the Snowball Riot (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - ALS [copy] from A. Whitney Griswold to students, 1959 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, statements, articles, clippings (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, statements, clippings from C. H. Sanford files (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Nuts and Cranks (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - 1959 March 13 - 16, 1957 March 17 - 20, 1959 March 22 March 31, 1959 April 1 - 1960 November 2 (Box 2, Folder 19-22)
      - Undated and duplicates (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Black arm bands, "14 Mar" (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Film reel (16 mm color): 1 video tape--dub of riot tape made by Anthony Moore (Y. 1959), 1 used cassette of audio recording (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Riot of 1918
    - Legal papers (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Calhoun College Incident, 1960
    - Notes and clippings (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Wright Hall Incident, 1969 November 3
    - Correspondence, statements, petitions [not restricted] (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Calhoun College incident Executive Committee papers, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
    Materials in Box 4, Folders 32-33 are restricted until January 1, 2036 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Wright Hall incident Executive Committee papers, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Materials in Box 4, Folder 33 are restricted until January 1, 2045 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
  - Hazing
    - Pledge not to haze members of the class of 1871. Signed by 40 members of the class of 1870 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Commencement Ticket Petition
    - Petition to Anson Phelps Stokes signed by 190 members of the class of 1921 asking for 2 tickets instead of 1 for each graduating student, 1921 April 16 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Valedictory Oration Petition, 1915
    - Anonymous petition to have Thomas A. Marshall and not John M. Clayton nor John D. Eccles give the Valedictory Oration (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Petition for Samuel S. Baldwin Y. 1801
    - Petition of the Sophomore Class to the Authority of Yale College to re-examine the punishment for his offence, circa 1799? (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Joseph Johnson Petition
    - An Indian of the Mohegan tribe--holograph petition to the students of Yale College, 1774 February 22 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Yale Women's Center, "Why the Symbols?", 1982 May 24 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - "We are Yale Seniors Against the War", 2007 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Protest of the class of 1830 to the censure of four classmates, 1828; Accession 19ND-A-380
  The materials are open for research.
  - Protest of the class of 1830 to the censure of four classmates, 1828 (Box AF4)
- Flyers documenting student life at Yale, circa 1960, 1991, undated; Accession 19ND-A-435
  - Flyers documenting student life at Yale, circa 1960, 1991, undated (Box 1)
- Open letter to Staughton Lynd, circa 1975; Accession 1979-A-034
  - Open letter from Daniel V. Manningham to Professor Staughton Lynd, circa 1975 (Box 1)
- Letter from J.D. Wilcox to Dr. Phelps Humphreys about the Medical School riot, 1823; Accession 1979-A-035
  - Letter from J.D. Wilcox to Dr. Phelps Humphreys about the Medical School riot, 1823 January 14 (Box 1)
- Report on events at the School of Organization and Management, 1988; Accession 1990-A-035
  - "A Note Describing Recent Events at the Yale School of Organization and Management," by Matthew C. Rogers '89, John C.A. Stevenson '89, Peter S. Szabo '90, 1988 November 28 (Box 1)
- "MAYDAY," a film made by Jericho Pictures for Yale Reports, 1970; Accession 2003-A-147
  - "MAYDAY," made by Jericho Pictures for Yale Reports, 1970; videotape (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Use copy, videotape (VHS) (Box 1U)
- "Stand with the resistance" poster, 1969; Accession 2009-A-089
  - "Stand with the resistance" poster, 1969 (Box 1)